What keeps us healthy and happy
as we go through life?
If you were going to invest now
in your future best self,
and your energy?
There was a recent survey of millennials
most important life goals were,
and over 80 percent said
was to get rich.
of those same young adults
said that another major life goal
was to become famous.
(Laughter)
to lean in to work, to push harder
and achieve more.
are the things that we need to go after
in order to have a good life.
Pictures of entire lives,
and how those choices work out for them,
are almost impossible to get.
Most of what we know about human life
to remember the past,
is anything but 20/20.
of what happens to us in life,
is downright creative.
But what if we could watch entire lives
as they unfold through time?
from the time that they were teenagers
all the way into old age
happy and healthy?
We did that.
The Harvard Study of Adult Development
of adult life that's ever been done.
the lives of 724 men,
their home lives, their health,
without knowing how their life stories
were going to turn out.
Studies like this are exceedingly rare.
fall apart within a decade
drop out of the study,
or funding for the research dries up,
or the researchers get distracted,
further down the field.
But through a combination of luck
of several generations of researchers,
this study has survived.
About 60 of our original 724 men
are still alive,
still participating in the study,
most of them in their 90s.
And we are now beginning to study
the more than 2,000 children of these men.
And I'm the fourth director of the study.
of two groups of men.
The first group started in the study
at Harvard College.
during World War II,
to serve in the war.
And the second group that we've followed
from Boston's poorest neighborhoods,
boys who were chosen for the study
from some of the most troubled
and disadvantaged families
in the Boston of the 1930s.
many without hot and cold running water.
When they entered the study,
all of these teenagers were interviewed.
They were given medical exams.
and we interviewed their parents.
grew up into adults
who entered all walks of life.
and bricklayers and doctors,
one President of the United States.
A few developed schizophrenia.
Some climbed the social ladder
all the way to the very top,
in the opposite direction.
The founders of this study
would never in their wildest dreams
standing here today, 75 years later,
the study still continues.
and dedicated research staff
and asks them if we can send them
about their lives.
Many of the inner city Boston men ask us,
My life just isn't that interesting."
The Harvard men never ask that question.
(Laughter)
of these lives,
we don't just send them questionnaires.
We interview them in their living rooms.
from their doctors.
We draw their blood, we scan their brains,
we talk to their children.
about their deepest concerns.
we finally asked the wives
as members of the study,
"You know, it's about time."
(Laughter)
So what have we learned?
from the tens of thousands of pages
of information that we've generated
on these lives?
or fame or working harder and harder.
from this 75-year study is this:
happier and healthier. Period.
about relationships.
are really good for us,
and that loneliness kills.
who are more socially connected
to family, to friends, to community,
and they live longer
than people who are less well connected.
turns out to be toxic.
than they want to be from others
find that they are less happy,
their health declines earlier in midlife,
their brain functioning declines sooner
than people who are not lonely.
is that at any given time,
will report that they're lonely.
can be lonely in a crowd
and you can be lonely in a marriage,
so the second big lesson that we learned
the number of friends you have,
you're in a committed relationship,
of your close relationships that matters.
of conflict is really bad for our health.
without much affection,
perhaps worse than getting divorced.
warm relationships is protective.
all the way into their 80s,
we wanted to look back at them at midlife
and to see if we could predict
into a happy, healthy octogenarian
and who wasn't.
everything we knew about them
at age 50,
cholesterol levels
were going to grow old.
in their relationships.
in their relationships at age 50
were the healthiest at age 80.
seem to buffer us
of getting old.
Our most happily partnered men and women
reported, in their 80s,
when they had more physical pain,
their mood stayed just as happy.
in unhappy relationships,
reported more physical pain,
it was magnified by more emotional pain.
about relationships and our health
don't just protect our bodies,
they protect our brains.
in a securely attached relationship
is protective,
that the people who are in relationships
on the other person in times of need,
stay sharper longer.
And the people in relationships
can't count on the other one,
earlier memory decline.
they don't have to be smooth all the time.
could bicker with each other
day in and day out,
could really count on the other
when the going got tough,
on their memories.
So this message,
are good for our health and well-being,
this is wisdom that's as old as the hills.
and so easy to ignore?
Well, we're human.
What we'd really like is a quick fix,
something we can get
and keep them that way.
and they're complicated
to family and friends,
it's not sexy or glamorous.
It's also lifelong. It never ends.
who were the happiest in retirement
to replace workmates with new playmates.
in that recent survey,
were starting out as young adults
and high achievement
to have a good life.
our study has shown
the people who leaned in to relationships,
with family, with friends, with community.
So what about you?
or you're 40, or you're 60.
to relationships even look like?
are practically endless.
as replacing screen time with people time
by doing something new together,
long walks or date nights,
who you haven't spoken to in years,
because those all-too-common family feuds
take a terrible toll
on the people who hold the grudges.
from Mark Twain.
More than a century ago,
he was looking back on his life,
and he wrote this:
"There isn't time, so brief is life,
heartburnings, callings to account.
There is only time for loving,
so to speak, for that."
with good relationships.
Thank you.
(Applause)